<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-15T18:58:37+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jackie Pease Zone</title><subtitle>Personal Website</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Biomaterials - Some Notes from the STEAMhouse Biobox course</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2021/02/15/biobox.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Biomaterials - Some Notes from the STEAMhouse Biobox course" /><published>2021-02-15T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-15T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2021/02/15/biobox</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2021/02/15/biobox.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently took part in &lt;a href=&quot;https://steamhouse.org.uk/events/biobox-workshop/&quot;&gt;STEAMhouse’s Biobox Workshop&lt;/a&gt; - along with &lt;a href=&quot;https://cheapjack.github.io/&quot;&gt;Ross Dalziel&lt;/a&gt;, a fellow member of &lt;a href=&quot;https://doesliverpool.com/&quot;&gt;DoES Liverpool&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://doesliverpool.github.io/Wearables/&quot;&gt;Wearable Tech Group&lt;/a&gt;. This was a 4 week course on Thursday mornings which aimed to combine “self-led materials research with live sessions where we will explore different areas related to materials development” and was led by Sarah King of STEAMhouse and Zoe Powell of Materiom. Also attending was &lt;a href=&quot;https://cheapjack.github.io/&quot;&gt;Ross Dalziel&lt;/a&gt;, a fellow member of &lt;a href=&quot;https://doesliverpool.com/&quot;&gt;DoES Liverpool&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://doesliverpool.github.io/Wearables/&quot;&gt;Wearable Tech Group&lt;/a&gt;. As part of this, we’d already done some experimentation with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DoESLiverpool/Wearables/wiki/Bio-Materials&quot;&gt;biomaterials and natural dyes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just before the course started, we received this excellent kit in the post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/contents_of_kit.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Biobox Kit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a good start, and I also had access to stuff we’d acquired previously for DoES Liverpool experiments, including a scale, heater stirrer, cornflour and ready ground cork, additional alginate, glycerol and agar, as well as some random containers to set materials in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I soon realised, though, that I’d get more out of the course by investing a bit in ingredients and equipment, and ended up buying a £25 dehydrator (after Ross had done the same), a cheap saucepan, silicone sheets, different types of carrageenan, methyl cellulose, spirulina and activated charcoal - one good thing is that so far this is all food-safe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/dehydrator.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Food Dehydrator&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were 4 Zoom meetings - one a week, where we discussed our experiments and Sarah and Zoe talked about the context of biomaterials use and gave us examples of practitioners working with everything from oyster shells to human hair; we also had a guest speaker, Sophie Hedderwick - she’s developing conductive biomaterials as well as working with natural dyes and inks, all really interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the last meeting everyone had 2 minutes to go through what they’d achieved - there were a wide range of interests from milk plastic to oak gall ink and one participant had done a lot of research on shells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I made: hopefully it will be useful in the future. From most of the pieces, you can see I didn’t do a good job of keeping the material flat - I think that’s the next thing to look into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agar Bioplastic - &lt;a href=&quot;https://materiom.org/recipe/41&quot;&gt;Materiom Recipe Ag02&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both these are pleasant materials. I accidentally added twice the specified amount of glycerol to the first sample, which has resulted in a clear and pliable material. The second sample is more rustly and less clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/agar_plastic_more_glycerol.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Agar Bioplastic with Extra Glycerol&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/agar_plastic.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Agar Bioplastic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eggshell Composite - &lt;a href=&quot;https://materiom.org/recipe/60&quot;&gt;Materiom Recipe Eg01&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was able to get a lot of eggshells from the cafe downstairs from DoES Liverpool, so made two batches, which came out more or less the same. I removed the membrane from inside the shells, dried them in the oven and then crushed them with a hammer (makeshift pestle and mortar). The material contains alginate and you pour vinegar over it to set it - this meant that it set much more quickly than the other materials. The output was hard and brittle and looked a bit like granite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/egg_shell.jpg?raw=true&quot;&gt;Eggshell Composite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coffee Composite - &lt;a href=&quot;https://materiom.org/recipe/171&quot;&gt;Materiom Recipe Co02&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This came out well - it’s another alginate recipe and when we tried it at DoES Liverpool it went mouldy before it dried). I did dry the coffee grounds in the oven before starting this time, and used the dehydrator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is slightly spongy, and dull looking - I don’t really like it aesthetically, but it seems quite strong and resistant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/coffee_composite.jpg?raw=true&quot;&gt;Coffee Composite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cork Composite - &lt;a href=&quot;https://materiom.org/recipe/40&quot;&gt;Materiom Recipe Cor03&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d also tried this before at DoES Liverpool, and still had all the ingredients, including ground up corks. The output material is hard and strong, and would probably be good for moulding if it doesn’t shrink too much when it sets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/coffee_composite.jpg?raw=true&quot;&gt;Cork Composite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">I recently took part in STEAMhouse’s Biobox Workshop - along with Ross Dalziel, a fellow member of DoES Liverpool’s Wearable Tech Group. This was a 4 week course on Thursday mornings which aimed to combine “self-led materials research with live sessions where we will explore different areas related to materials development” and was led by Sarah King of STEAMhouse and Zoe Powell of Materiom. Also attending was Ross Dalziel, a fellow member of DoES Liverpool’s Wearable Tech Group. As part of this, we’d already done some experimentation with biomaterials and natural dyes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">15 Minute Liverpool - Familiar Sights</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/08/26/familiar-sights.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="15 Minute Liverpool - Familiar Sights" /><published>2020-08-26T19:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-26T19:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/08/26/familiar-sights</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/08/26/familiar-sights.html">&lt;p&gt;When I wrote my first post I intended to get out and explore the area around DoES Liverpool on at least 2 lunchtimes per week. It’s been more than a month and I’ve only made 2 more trips, and only now got round to writing them up…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first trip was down to St George’s Plateau and then half way down Dale Street on 30 July, a beautiful warm and sunny day - I must have been walking fast to get that far, as it’s outside the 15 minute isochrone on Adrian’s map; it took me more than 20 minutes on the way back, uphill and in the heat:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eNoG6cgYBic&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of the Fabric District and into an area of large spaces and student apartments where the architects might have had a bit of fun applying different surface textures and patterns to buildings which have the same basic structure.
Then past grand classical buildings containing the city’s great cultural institutions. It certainly seems feasible to make a short visit to the art gallery or library on a lunch break from DoES Liverpool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the top half of Dale Street contains some excellent pubs, along with offices and sandwich shops. I returned along a slightly different route, past tourist cafes, Egyptian themed outcrops of the Birkenhead tunnel and a basrelief drum commemorating the victims of Hillsborough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a really lovely walk and shows the richness of the city easily accessible from Kempston Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second trip was on 17 August, to the city centre shops, my first visit since before lockdown. I started off via London Road, a mixture of older buildings, replacement apartment blocks and world food shops. There are some nice new outdoor spaces, with places to sit, and an unreconstructed market, before you get to the main street which is busy with buses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YJBjtYwBHpQ&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then went past the railway hotel and Lime Street station, fronted by a large new plaza, before crossing the road, down past the front of St John’s Shopping Centre and down through the busy pedestrianised area to Marks and Spencer. I hadn’t left a whole hour for the trip, so there wasn’t really time to do anything except buy a quick snack before returning in the same direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it took me until Tuesday morning to put the photos together and load them onto YouTube. This time I used Adobe Rush, which was pretty quick - I didn’t crop or straighten the photos and I didn’t do any editing apart from adding titles. Ideally I’d like the time for each photo to be less, or to be able to flick through them as stills. I still haven’t worked out how to set up a website, so that’s the next thing, but at least I can link this page to my Instagram account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back at these trips, they both cover ground that feels very familiar and safe to me - I want to start looking at parts of the area I know less well and see what facilities they have to offer. I think I should start looking for particular features that might be worth recording and that tell us something about the local area. I think what I’ve been doing so far is very tangential to the 15 minute city idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adrian’s McEwen’s isochrone maps, which I’m using to judge how far I should be able to walk in 15 minutes, can be found here: &lt;a href=&quot;trips.mcqn.com&quot;&gt;trips.mcqn.com&lt;/a&gt;, and I read an interesting article today about what it might mean for Camden here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/camden-town-unlimited/beyond-the-pandemic-the-prospect-of-a-15-minute-city-693b6a24e438&quot;&gt;https://medium.com/camden-town-unlimited/beyond-the-pandemic-the-prospect-of-a-15-minute-city-693b6a24e438&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">When I wrote my first post I intended to get out and explore the area around DoES Liverpool on at least 2 lunchtimes per week. It’s been more than a month and I’ve only made 2 more trips, and only now got round to writing them up…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">15 Minute Liverpool - First Look at the 15 Minute City</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/07/18/first-look.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="15 Minute Liverpool - First Look at the 15 Minute City" /><published>2020-07-18T15:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-18T15:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/07/18/first-look</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/07/18/first-look.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen a lot about 15 minute cities recently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“this simple notion that all your basic everyday needs, from education to commerce to health care to culture and so on, are located within 15 minutes walk or bike of your front door”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how it might work - do people get to mix? Might you lose the special things you get in a city centre when you have to endlessly repeat the basics? I like having a pub near my house, but I’m definitely prepared to travel slightly further to exhibitions, libraries and well-equiped maker spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an interesting way of looking at we do need though, and how we can move away from cars to cycling and walking more - this seems like a good time to think about things when everything has already been shaken up by the COVID crisis - for me that means that the office I usually work from in Greater Manchester is closed, and I’m working from the coworking space at &lt;a href=&quot;doesliverpool.com&quot;&gt;DoES Liverpool&lt;/a&gt; (just over half an hour’s cycling from my home, so it doesn’t quite fit into the 15 minute city idea, but I love cycling into work- it gives me time to think and stuff to look at, and it’s good for you).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like a good lunchtime project to start by exploring the area around DoES Liverpool - Adrian McEwen has been working on isochrone maps which show how far you can get in 15 minutes by cycling or walking (including for people with mobility issues) - you can find out more here: &lt;a href=&quot;trips.mcqn.com&quot;&gt;trips.mcqn.com&lt;/a&gt;. Here’s one of his maps showing how far you can get from DoES Liverpool in 15 minutes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/15-minute-liverpool/15-minutes-from-does-liverpool.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;15 minutes from DoES Liverpool&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started by just walking to Rodney Street and back on Monday lunchtime - it took exactly half an hour, so the map is accurate, at least for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/CnIKAuULK7w&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure there’s lots more thought that can be put into this. For anyone else who’s interested, here’s a few links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adrian’s isochrone maps, as mentioned before: &lt;a href=&quot;trips.mcqn.com&quot;&gt;trips.mcqn.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 15 minute city repository in Github/Liverpool-UK: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Liverpool-UK/somebody-should/issues/35&quot;&gt;https://github.com/Liverpool-UK/somebody-should/issues/35&lt;/a&gt; - lots of opportunity for people in Liverpool to get involved&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And 2 articles on Paris: one from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/carltonreid/2020/01/21/phasing-out-cars-key-to-paris-mayors-plans-for-15-minute-city/#5ccba7706952&quot;&gt;Forbes&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://annehidalgo2020.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/01/Dossier-de-presse-Le-Paris-du-quart-dheure.pdf&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; (in French) from the site of Paris mayor Anne Hidalgo.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">I’ve seen a lot about 15 minute cities recently: “this simple notion that all your basic everyday needs, from education to commerce to health care to culture and so on, are located within 15 minutes walk or bike of your front door”.</summary></entry></feed>