<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jackie Pease Zone</title>
    <description>Personal Website</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 14:52:53 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 14:52:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Embroidery x Glue - A Weekend of Experimenting</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A bit of experimenting, mainly last weekend, with machine embroidery and glue film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glue film was inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jarkman&quot;&gt;Richard Sewell&lt;/a&gt; who came along to the latest online &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DoESLiverpool/somebody-should/wiki/Wearable-Technology-Group&quot;&gt;DoES Liverpool Wearable Tech meetup&lt;/a&gt;, and as well as showing us his amazing &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AirGiantsHQ&quot;&gt;inflatable robots&lt;/a&gt;, also showed us some fabric folding techniques, using a stiffer fabric ironed on with &lt;a href=&quot;http://mcb-supplies.co.uk/HotMeltWoodVeneerAdhesive.html&quot;&gt;glue film&lt;/a&gt; to provide structure. I’m quite interested in folded structures e.g. this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CI1Jl_HH6uM/?igshid=nx9a0mnhp1ky&quot;&gt;tree&lt;/a&gt;, so ordered some of the glue film to try out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we’ve got a new embroidery machine, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DoESLiverpool/somebody-should/wiki/Embroidery-Machine-Fred&quot;&gt;Fred&lt;/a&gt; at DoESLiverpool, and it seemed worth looking at whether that had any potential as a way to stiffen fabric for folding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used my current favourite tool, &lt;a href=&quot;https://p5js.org/&quot;&gt;p5js&lt;/a&gt; to create an svg file (similar to the one I’d used for the tree). Admittedly this took me a lot longer than it would have taken with a CAD package, but it meant that I could easily change the number of rows and columns. I imported the file into &lt;a href=&quot;https://inkscape.org/&quot;&gt;Inkscape&lt;/a&gt; and used the &lt;a href=&quot;https://inkstitch.org/&quot;&gt;Ink/Stitch&lt;/a&gt; extension to create the .pes file used by the embroidery machine. I also exported it as as a dxf for use in the laser cutter - I love that you can the same base file with so many different CNC machines!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my first attempt, I started with 2 layers of scrap non-woven polypropylene and a layer of stabiliser. I was impressed by the way the embroidery looked, but I found it too difficult to keep the folds in position, and having lots of rows made it extra complicated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/1st_attempt_emb_column.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1st_attempt_emb_column.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/1st_attempt_back.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1st_attempt_back.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/1st_attempt_fold.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1st_attempt_fold.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gave up and tried again with a softer fabric, fewer rows and more columns. This also looked great just flat. The interesting black and white effect isn’t intentional - the bobbin hadn’t been threaded properly, so the tension was wrong and the bobbin thread showed on the front (something to try to recreate by blending colours though!):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/2nd_attempt_tension.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2nd_attempt_tension.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/2nd_attempt_front.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2nd_attempt_front.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/2nd_attempt_back.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2nd_attempt_back.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I removed the stabliser between the triangles, hoping this would give more flexibility. It was very difficult to get get the triangles to stay in position once folded, but after sticking the edges together to make a tube shape, it did eventually work (someone said this looked like a caterpillar, so that might be something to work on - I’d like to try adding servos…):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/2nd_attempt_folded.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2nd_attempt_folded.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the 3rd attempt I decided to use 2 layers of embroidery (actually 2 layers of fill stitch + 2 backing layers), made the triangles a bit bigger for easier folding and reduced the space between triangles. Disadvantages, not enough triangles round to make a column shape (this was the most that would fit in the hoop - there is a way to piece bigger embroideries together, so I’ll be looking into that), plus it uses lots of thread and is hard work for the machine. It did fold really easily and is quite a nice object to hold:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/3rd_attempt_front.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;3rd_attempt_front.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/3rd_attempt_folded.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;3rd_attempt_folded.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more go, with smaller triangles and only 1 layer of embroidery - this took a lot of manual folding before the folds fell into place, but once it did, the structure seemed pretty stable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/4th_attempt_front.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;4th_attempt_front.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/4th_attempt_folded.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;4th_attempt_folded.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whie waiting for the embroidery machine (it does take a while), I tried out the glue sheets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cut out a piece of glue sheet, then ironed it onto the back of some thick satin curtain fabric brought in by Karen, who I’m working with on another project. As Karen was laser cutting some chain maille, we decided to use that as a test:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/satin_glue.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;satin_glue.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/satin_laser_cutting.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;satin_laser_cutting.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After laser cutting, you need to remove the backing sheet, and then iron on to a substrate. We used baking paper to stop the glue sticking to the iron - the baking paper stuck to the fabric though, so not the best:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/satin_separating.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;satin_separating.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results were good, both with the left over teardrop shapes, and with the chain maille:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/satin_teardrops.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;satin_teardrops.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/satin_on_velvet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;satin_on_velvet.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then tried the folding pattern on 3mm ply. After laser cutting the ply we replaced the triangles with the glue side up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/ply_laser_cutting.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ply_laser_cutting.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/ply_glue.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ply_glue.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/ply_ironing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ply_ironing.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a fine soft fabric meant that the glue came through to the back. It also tended to spread a bit round the edges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/ply_back_fabric.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ply_back_fabric.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ply stuck well, but the output wasn’t really suitable for folding&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/ply_lifting.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ply_lifting.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/ply_on_fabric.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ply_on_fabric.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve got a lot of polypropylene at DoES Liverpool, so it seemed worth trying that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/pp_laser_cutting.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pp_laser_cutting.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It did fold quite well, but as with embroidery, it would have been better with narrower channels in between the shapes. The polypropylene stuck well to begin with, but after a few days of being flexed it began to come away from the fabric. It might be better to use something more flexible if it’s designed to be moved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/pp_folded.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pp_folded.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also ironed the waste polypropylene on to some gauze; the glue spread badly because the fabric couldn’t absorb it, and the baking paper stuck. I washed this in an attempt to remove the soot from the laser cutter (it didn’t) and the glue seemed unaffected:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/pp_gauze.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pp_gauze.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, we ironed some foil sheets onto the waste ply - this would have probably worked better if we’d waited for the glue to set, but still a pretty nice distressed effect after a couple of sheets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/ply_foil.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ply_foil.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not quite sure where this is going, but maybe my next step will be to try some more flexible materials with the glue method and articulating some of the folding structures.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blogpost/2021/03/21/embroidery-x-glue.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blogpost/2021/03/21/embroidery-x-glue.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blogpost</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Biomaterials - Some Notes from the STEAMhouse Biobox course</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently took part in &lt;a href=&quot;https://steamhouse.org.uk/events/biobox-workshop/&quot;&gt;STEAMhouse’s Biobox Workshop&lt;/a&gt;, an excellent 4 week course combining “self-led materials research with live sessions [exploring] different areas related to materials development”, led by Sarah King of STEAMhouse and Zoe Powell of Materiom. &lt;a href=&quot;https://cheapjack.github.io/&quot;&gt;Ross Dalziel&lt;/a&gt; was also on the course - we’d both already done a bit of experimenting with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DoESLiverpool/Wearables/wiki/Bio-Materials&quot;&gt;biomaterials and natural dyes&lt;/a&gt; at DoES Liverpool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just before the course started, we received this really nice kit in the post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/contents_of_kit.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Biobox Kit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good start, and I also had access to the stuff we already had at DoES Liverpool, including a scale, heater stirrer, cornflour and ready ground cork, additional alginate, glycerol and agar, as well as some random containers to set materials in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I soon realised, though, that I’d get more out of the course by investing a bit in ingredients and equipment, and ended up buying a £25 dehydrator (after Ross had done the same), a cheap saucepan, silicone sheets, different types of carrageenan, methyl cellulose, spirulina and activated charcoal - one good thing is that so far this is all food-safe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/dehydrator.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Food Dehydrator&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were 4 Zoom meetings - one a week, where we discussed our experiments and Sarah and Zoe talked about the context of biomaterials use and gave us examples of practitioners working with everything from oyster shells to human hair; we also had a great guest speaker, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sophiehedderwick.com&quot;&gt;Sophie Hedderwick&lt;/a&gt; - she’s developing conductive biomaterials as well as working with natural dyes and inks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the last meeting everyone had 2 minutes to go through what they’d achieved - there were a wide range of interests from milk plastic to oak gall ink and one participant had done a lot of research on shells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I made, take a look if you think you might be interested in DIY biomaterials. From most of the pieces, you can see I didn’t do a good job of keeping the material flat - that would be a goodd think to look into next. I’m sure I’ll be carrying on with this, especially the conductive materials, but I also really liked the carageenan leather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agar Bioplastic - &lt;a href=&quot;https://materiom.org/recipe/41&quot;&gt;Materiom Recipe Ag02&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both these are pleasant materials. I accidentally added twice the specified amount of glycerol to the first sample, which has resulted in a clear and pliable material. The second sample is more rustly and less clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/agar_plastic_more_glycerol.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Agar Bioplastic with Extra Glycerol&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/agar_plastic.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Agar Bioplastic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eggshell Composite - &lt;a href=&quot;https://materiom.org/recipe/60&quot;&gt;Materiom Recipe Eg01&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was able to get a lot of eggshells from the cafe downstairs from DoES Liverpool, so made two batches, which came out more or less the same. I removed the membrane from inside the shells, dried them in the oven and then crushed them with a hammer (makeshift pestle and mortar). The material contains alginate and you pour vinegar over it to set it - this meant that it set much more quickly than the other materials. The output was hard and brittle and looked a bit like granite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/egg_shell.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Eggshell Composite&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coffee Composite - &lt;a href=&quot;https://materiom.org/recipe/171&quot;&gt;Materiom Recipe Co02&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This came out well - it’s another alginate recipe and when we tried it before at DoES Liverpool it went mouldy before it dried. I did dry the coffee grounds in the oven before starting this time, and used the dehydrator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is slightly spongy, and dull looking - I don’t really like it aesthetically, but it seems quite strong and resistant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/coffee_composite.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Coffee Composite&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cork Composite - &lt;a href=&quot;https://materiom.org/recipe/40&quot;&gt;Materiom Recipe Cor03&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d also tried this before at DoES Liverpool, and still had all the ingredients, including ground up corks. The output material is hard and strong, and would probably be good for moulding if it doesn’t shrink too much when it sets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/cork.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Cork Composite&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spirulina and Carageenan Iota ‘Leather’ - &lt;a href=&quot;https://materiom.org/recipe/191&quot;&gt;Materiom Recipe Ca02&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d been inspired by Sophie Hedderwick’s talk about conductive materials at this stage, but the activated charcoal I needed still hadn’t arrived, so I decided to have a go at this recipe. I didn’t have any sage dye, so added 4ml of Spirulina powder, something else that the Materiom site suggests as a colourant. What I learned: by the time it dried out (seaweed recipes typically take several days), this produced a thin and fragile film - it’s quite smooth and has a lovely bottle green colour though, so I’ll try to use it for something. Next time I’ll pour it into a thicker mould though (and smaller so it fits in the dehydrator), and use less water to start off with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/spirulina_carageenan.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Carrageenan Iota and Spirulina&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conductive Materials! - Based on Materiom Recipes &lt;a href=&quot;https://materiom.org/recipe/191&quot;&gt;Ca02&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://materiom.org/recipe/212&quot;&gt;CoF 01&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The activated charcoal I’d ordered from eBay finally arrived. Sophie’s experiments used the Materiom recipe &lt;a href=&quot;https://materiom.org/recipe/208&quot;&gt;Ge04&lt;/a&gt; “Conductive Gelatin bioplastic” and the material she produced looked glossy and pliable material. I didn’t really want to use gelatin so decided to try a couple of plant-based recipes. The first was the Carageenan Iota recipe I used above. I added 16g of activated charcoal instead of the Spirulina and used a plastic box as a mould. Again it took a long time to dry and curled up a lot when I used the dehydrator. The second recipe was for Coconut Fibre and Agar Bioplastic - activated charcoal is made from coconut fibre, so it seemed reasonable to substitute it. I added 19g. This agar bioplastic dried a lot faster than the seaweed one, but I still used the dehydrator and it still curled up a bit. Despite containing glycerol both materials were hard and dull looking, but seem quite strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tested both with a multimeter and also used them as part of a circuit to light an LED. They’re both conductive (the carageenan biomaterial seemed more conductive than the agar one in this test) and I think could have some interesting uses in future projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/activated_charcoal.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Activated Charcoal Biomaterials&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/multimeter_agar.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Testing Agar Biomaterial&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/biobox/multimeter_carageenan_2.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Testing Carageenan Biomaterial&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Sarah and Zoe and everyone else involved in this course - definitely recommended if you get a chance!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blogpost/2021/02/16/biobox.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blogpost/2021/02/16/biobox.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blogpost</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>15 Minute Liverpool - Familiar Sights</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When I wrote my first post I intended to get out and explore the area around DoES Liverpool on at least 2 lunchtimes per week. It’s been more than a month and I’ve only made 2 more trips, and only now got round to writing them up…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first trip was down to St George’s Plateau and then half way down Dale Street on 30 July, a beautiful warm and sunny day - I must have been walking fast to get that far, as it’s outside the 15 minute isochrone on Adrian’s map; it took me more than 20 minutes on the way back, uphill and in the heat:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eNoG6cgYBic&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of the Fabric District and into an area of large spaces and student apartments where the architects might have had a bit of fun applying different surface textures and patterns to buildings which have the same basic structure.
Then past grand classical buildings containing the city’s great cultural institutions. It certainly seems feasible to make a short visit to the art gallery or library on a lunch break from DoES Liverpool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the top half of Dale Street contains some excellent pubs, along with offices and sandwich shops. I returned along a slightly different route, past tourist cafes, Egyptian themed outcrops of the Birkenhead tunnel and a basrelief drum commemorating the victims of Hillsborough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a really lovely walk and shows the richness of the city easily accessible from Kempston Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second trip was on 17 August, to the city centre shops, my first visit since before lockdown. I started off via London Road, a mixture of older buildings, replacement apartment blocks and world food shops. There are some nice new outdoor spaces, with places to sit, and an unreconstructed market, before you get to the main street which is busy with buses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YJBjtYwBHpQ&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then went past the railway hotel and Lime Street station, fronted by a large new plaza, before crossing the road, down past the front of St John’s Shopping Centre and down through the busy pedestrianised area to Marks and Spencer. I hadn’t left a whole hour for the trip, so there wasn’t really time to do anything except buy a quick snack before returning in the same direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it took me until Tuesday morning to put the photos together and load them onto YouTube. This time I used Adobe Rush, which was pretty quick - I didn’t crop or straighten the photos and I didn’t do any editing apart from adding titles. Ideally I’d like the time for each photo to be less, or to be able to flick through them as stills. I still haven’t worked out how to set up a website, so that’s the next thing, but at least I can link this page to my Instagram account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back at these trips, they both cover ground that feels very familiar and safe to me - I want to start looking at parts of the area I know less well and see what facilities they have to offer. I think I should start looking for particular features that might be worth recording and that tell us something about the local area. I think what I’ve been doing so far is very tangential to the 15 minute city idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adrian’s McEwen’s isochrone maps, which I’m using to judge how far I should be able to walk in 15 minutes, can be found here: &lt;a href=&quot;trips.mcqn.com&quot;&gt;trips.mcqn.com&lt;/a&gt;, and I read an interesting article today about what it might mean for Camden here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/camden-town-unlimited/beyond-the-pandemic-the-prospect-of-a-15-minute-city-693b6a24e438&quot;&gt;https://medium.com/camden-town-unlimited/beyond-the-pandemic-the-prospect-of-a-15-minute-city-693b6a24e438&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2020 19:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blogpost/2020/08/26/familiar-sights.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blogpost/2020/08/26/familiar-sights.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blogpost</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>15 Minute Liverpool - First Look at the 15 Minute City</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen a lot about 15 minute cities recently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“this simple notion that all your basic everyday needs, from education to commerce to health care to culture and so on, are located within 15 minutes walk or bike of your front door”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how it might work - do people get to mix? Might you lose the special things you get in a city centre when you have to endlessly repeat the basics? I like having a pub near my house, but I’m definitely prepared to travel slightly further to exhibitions, libraries and well-equiped maker spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an interesting way of looking at we do need though, and how we can move away from cars to cycling and walking more - this seems like a good time to think about things when everything has already been shaken up by the COVID crisis - for me that means that the office I usually work from in Greater Manchester is closed, and I’m working from the coworking space at &lt;a href=&quot;doesliverpool.com&quot;&gt;DoES Liverpool&lt;/a&gt; (just over half an hour’s cycling from my home, so it doesn’t quite fit into the 15 minute city idea, but I love cycling into work- it gives me time to think and stuff to look at, and it’s good for you).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like a good lunchtime project to start by exploring the area around DoES Liverpool - Adrian McEwen has been working on isochrone maps which show how far you can get in 15 minutes by cycling or walking (including for people with mobility issues) - you can find out more here: &lt;a href=&quot;trips.mcqn.com&quot;&gt;trips.mcqn.com&lt;/a&gt;. Here’s one of his maps showing how far you can get from DoES Liverpool in 15 minutes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/15-minute-liverpool/15-minutes-from-does-liverpool.jpg?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;15 minutes from DoES Liverpool&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started by just walking to Rodney Street and back on Monday lunchtime - it took exactly half an hour, so the map is accurate, at least for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/CnIKAuULK7w&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure there’s lots more thought that can be put into this. For anyone else who’s interested, here’s a few links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adrian’s isochrone maps, as mentioned before: &lt;a href=&quot;trips.mcqn.com&quot;&gt;trips.mcqn.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The 15 minute city repository in Github/Liverpool-UK: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Liverpool-UK/somebody-should/issues/35&quot;&gt;https://github.com/Liverpool-UK/somebody-should/issues/35&lt;/a&gt; - lots of opportunity for people in Liverpool to get involved&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And 2 articles on Paris: one from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/carltonreid/2020/01/21/phasing-out-cars-key-to-paris-mayors-plans-for-15-minute-city/#5ccba7706952&quot;&gt;Forbes&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://annehidalgo2020.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/01/Dossier-de-presse-Le-Paris-du-quart-dheure.pdf&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; (in French) from the site of Paris mayor Anne Hidalgo.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 15:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blogpost/2020/07/18/first-look.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blogpost/2020/07/18/first-look.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blogpost</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
