<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jackie Pease Zone</title>
    <description>Personal Website</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2022 18:21:15 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2022 18:21:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week Notes - My Bike&apos;s Got LED (Of Course)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you know me, you might be aware that I’m quite keen on addressable LEDs, so, while I already had a light up backpack for cycling (a prototype for &lt;a href=&quot;https://peloton.coop&quot;&gt;Peloton Liverpool&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/PelotonLiv/status/1499019125011668996?s=20&amp;amp;t=nDrJC5sKxXCYXhn_cV9HPQ&quot;&gt;Disco breastplates&lt;/a&gt;), I couldn’t resist buying a &lt;a href=&quot;https://mcqn.com/&quot;&gt;MCQN Ltd&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/huffeec/status/1585560542080638979?s=20&amp;amp;t=gtIk50p2UsO_uZefMUf0Gg&quot;&gt;My Bike’s Got LED board&lt;/a&gt; after watching the flurry of activity here at DoES Liverpool as Adrian and Chris got the first batch ready - they were launching with Peloton Liverpool Joyride cyclists taking part in &lt;a href=&quot;https://katumba.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Katumba Drumming&lt;/a&gt;’s Halloween event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great night (more detail in Chris’s post &lt;a href=&quot;https://mcqn.com/posts/2022-10-31-weeks-889-891-More-Bikes-got-LED/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). I didn’t quite get my lights ready in time, but a few cable ties the next morning was all it took to finish the job:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;How my bike might have looked at yesterday&amp;#39;s excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KatumbaBloco?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@KatumbaBloco&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/halloweenparade?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#halloweenparade&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/PelotonLiv?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@PelotonLiv&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/joyride?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#joyride&lt;/a&gt; if I&amp;#39;d fitted my &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MCQN_Ltd?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@MCQN_Ltd&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/mybikesgotled?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#mybikesgotled&lt;/a&gt; board in time.&lt;br /&gt;Everyone else&amp;#39;s looked fantastic though and mine is now ready for future trips.&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeknotes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#weeknotes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/6bPZrMqE2M&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/6bPZrMqE2M&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jackie Pease (@jackie_pease) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/1586751768901419010?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;October 30, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boards use open source &lt;a href=&quot;https://kno.wled.ge/&quot;&gt;WLED software&lt;/a&gt;, which makes it easy to control a variety of addressable LEDs (WS2812 in this case) via wifi using a phone app or your computer. At it’s simplest you can just set the number of lights, choose an effect, apply colour and speed settings and you’re ready to go. In this case, I had 2 rows of LEDs, divided into 3 parts each, so it made sense to put a little bit more work in and define segments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just a case of telling WLED the starting and ending position of each segment - some of the LEDs on my bike are hidden under black heatshrink so I haven’t included them in the segments. Depending on the layout you can reverse the order that a segment lights up in, or even set it as a mirror of the previous segment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20221107/segments.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;segments.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t easily use the mirror option as my layout wasn’t symmetrical:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20221107/lights_diagram.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lights_diagram.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That might be something to consider next time, although the Reverse Direction option has worked well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to save all your settings, including segments, in presets, otherwise you’ll lose them when you switch the board off, and it isn’t difficult to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Aircoookie/WLED/issues/146&quot;&gt;backup your settings to JSON files&lt;/a&gt; either. From your browser, just type in the following 2 commands:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[WLED-IP]/edit?download=cfg.json&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;[WLED-IP]/edit?download=presets.json&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where [WLED-IP] is the IP address of your board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good thing about WLED is that it’s so easy to get started, although there’s a lot more you can do if you want. I’m looking forward to some sound reactive stuff, as the group cycle rides organised by Peloton Liverpool nearly always have music; it would be good to be able to sync effects across the whole group too. I think Adrian and Chris have some of this planned for their v2 board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the board makes things easy too - you could buy a dev board and source all the components yourself, but it’s good to be able to move straight on to the fun bit and know it’ll work.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2022/11/07/Weeknotes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2022/11/07/Weeknotes.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>weeknotes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week Notes - You Win or You Learn</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A quote from Nelson Mandela apparently. It’s been in my head recently as I spent several days working on an LED project I shouldn’t have agreed to do with too little time, too little experience with the tools I eventually had to use, and without ever getting to see the physical installation. It feels like I’ve learnt a lot though and I’m inspired to learn more. So here’s a few rough notes, so I don’t forget, and in case there’s anything useful to other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sensors&quot;&gt;Sensors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally there was a plan to use a sensor to control the speed that the lights moved and their brightness.  I experimented with several different inputs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;potentiometer&quot;&gt;Potentiometer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20221026/esp32_with_potentiometer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;esp32_with_potentiometer.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sensingthecity.com/controlling-an-addressable-led-strip-with-any-sensor/&quot;&gt;this code from Sensing the City&lt;/a&gt; to make a light move along a strip of LEDs (it looks even better if it’s moving around a disk!). Sensing the City is a great site, with loads of other good ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;capacitive-touch-sensor&quot;&gt;Capacitive Touch Sensor&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20221026/capacitive_touch.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;capacitive_touch.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already had an Adafruit CAP1188 breakout, recommended to me by Chris E at the Friday night cycling group I go to. It was easy to set up following &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.adafruit.com/adafruit-cap1188-breakout&quot;&gt;the instructions on the Adafruit site&lt;/a&gt; and worked well, although I didn’t go further than blinking the onboard lights on this occasion. It seems worth putting in a bit more time and investigating some of its other features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I didn’t get to use the Azoteq pressure sensor originally suggested for the project, I did see an Arduino sketch that used it. It looks as though there’s more to set up, but apparently it is very reliable, so might be worth further investigation too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pressure-sensors&quot;&gt;Pressure Sensors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve used home made pressure sensors a lot at DoES Liverpool, mainly because we’ve found them a bit more predictable than capacitive touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I refamiliarised myself with these foam/wire/Velostat sensors that we made for &lt;a href=&quot;https://getamoveon.ac.uk/events/what-does-health-look-like&quot;&gt;Laura Pullig / Lanacaster Univerity’s What Does Health Look Like? project&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SoleRebelTapUK?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@SoleRebelTapUK&lt;/a&gt; testing out pressure sensors &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DoESLiverpool?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@DoESLiverpool&lt;/a&gt; for ‘What Does Health look like’ with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidaellis?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@davidaellis&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/GAMONetwork?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@GAMONetwork&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/8pqFMPdOW1&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/8pqFMPdOW1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; laura pullig (@Laura_pullig) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Laura_pullig/status/1094233839629680640?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 9, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They work well and can use similar code to the potentiometer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with Chris T, I also refurbished one of these much larger, but functionally similar, pressure sensors from &lt;a href=&quot;https://mcqn.com/ibal191/&quot;&gt;MCQN Ltd’s Play the Tree/Geometric Lights&lt;/a&gt;. There are another 3 of these at DoES Liverpool and we’re now thinking of new uses for them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20221026/large_pressure_sensor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;large_pressure_sensor.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mapping-irregular-led-layouts&quot;&gt;Mapping Irregular LED Layouts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project involved a fairly large number of pixels, arranged irregularly. In the end some of the pixels weren’t added until the day before the project shipped, so they had to be laid out physically in the order they would light up. I did try out several tools that might help me do pixel mapping in future though:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;xlights-generate-custom-model&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://manual.xlights.org/xlights/chapters/chapter-five-menus/tools/generate-custom-model&quot;&gt;xLights Generate Custom Model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried this before, and I didn’t have any more luck this time. The consensus seems to be that you need a decent camera, so I think it’s going to be worth borrowing one, watching a bunch of YouTubes, and trying again. On the other hand, I did find out that you can now control WLED via wifi from xLights on your laptop, so all good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/aaknitt/pixel_mapper&quot;&gt;semi-automatic pixel mapper&lt;/a&gt; might also be worth investigating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;led-mapper-by-jason-coon&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jasoncoon.github.io/led-mapper/&quot;&gt;LED-Mapper&lt;/a&gt; by Jason Coon&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is great - you do have to use Google Sheets to create a layout first, but it then allows you “to generate and visualize maps for irregular and/or gapped LED layouts, for use with FastLED, Pixelblaze and other libraries” and “also generates coordinate maps for radius and angle.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used both a disk of regularly spaced rings (wired as a spiral) and an irregular spiral made from WS2811 Xmas tree style pixels, taped onto Correx. Both were good although obviously the more closely-packed disk shows the pattern much better. This Tweet shows the regular disk running Jason Coon’s example sketch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Disappointingly I haven&amp;#39;t got &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/xlights?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#xlights&lt;/a&gt; Generate Custom Model to work yet, so have been using laser cut PP grids, then switching on LEDs sequentially, in order to get them into the spreadsheet to start off with...&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeknotes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#weeknotes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/sp6eTwJbZE&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/sp6eTwJbZE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jackie Pease (@jackie_pease) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/1576696560481509376?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;October 2, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used laser-cut polypropylene grids to work out the coordinates of the pixels, but Jason replied to the Tweet recommending &lt;a href=&quot;http://app.bhencke.com/pixelmap.html&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, which should be easier and more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put together a quick push button circuit on the Arduino to help me identify the next pixel in line in the irregular spiral, and I can see that being useful again. The sketch is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/JackiePease/LEDTests/tree/main/Button_LED&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;raspberry-pi-as-localhost-with-several-esp32s-running-wled-or-picows&quot;&gt;Raspberry Pi as localhost with several ESP32s running WLED (or PicoWs?)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing I didn’t get very far with before it became apparent that we weren’t going to use it, but I found some easy to follow instructions &lt;a href=&quot;https://pimylifeup.com/raspberry-pi-mosquitto-mqtt-server/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.sparkfun.com/tutorials/setting-up-a-raspberry-pi-3-as-an-access-point/introduction&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I’d like to take this further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some alternatives to mqtt that might be worth looking at too - e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LkGCo9Gi8mk&quot;&gt;this YouTube&lt;/a&gt; shows how to make a lightshow with WLED, FPP, xLights and DDP data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arduino-mega-2560&quot;&gt;Arduino Mega 2560&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was what I finally wrote the sketch on, as there was one on site and I had one here. Memory was a bit of an issue,  and because I didn’t get to see the final output, I wasn’t able to easily make amendments when things didn’t work as the users wanted (another lesson learned is that it might have helped to demonstrate the kind of effects that can be created at the start, and with what density of pixels).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Adrian and Chris T for advice on C++ (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/JackiePease/LEDTests/tree/main/October_LED_Project&quot;&gt;the current spaghetti&lt;/a&gt; is my responsibility).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I still want to do more LED projects…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2022/10/26/Weeknotes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2022/10/26/Weeknotes.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>weeknotes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week Notes - All The Pens</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Having done some maintenance on the pen plotter last month, I’ve mainly been experimenting with different pens and papers to see what effects they produce. I am aiming to use more refillable pens, but having been asked to produce a flower picture in the style of one of my earlier pen plots, it’s been more Sharpies, fineliners and gel pens recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I forgot to take photos of that picture before handing it over, unfortunately - one issue was that the sky in the background was quite light and came out uncoloured in the plot, which was a strong contrast to areas which were heavily filled with Sharpie and Uniball Eye fineliner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also had problems knowing how long pens would last, particularly Sharpies, and trying to guess where to restart the gcode from once one had run out was leading to doubled lines and missed areas. As a test, I plotted this picture (approx. A5) repeatedly until the red pen ran out, so now I know it’ll do about 2.5 of those (I like the version with less red ink best though). These also include a bit of experimenting with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pentel.co.uk/product/pentel-hybrid-dual-metallic-gel-pen-k110/&quot;&gt;Pentel Hybrid Dual Metallic Gel Pens&lt;/a&gt;. My main conclusion is that although pretty, you need to go over the lines twice to get a good result and that uses nearly a whole pen for this size, so a bit expensive for this application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20220501/sharpie_testing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;sharpie_testing.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plotted the original picture on Pergamino paper, and I think the texture of the paper and the fact that Sharpie ink doesn’t soak into it as much makes this more successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20220501/roses_on_pergamino.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;roses_on_pergamino.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s all been &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SonarSonic/DrawingBotV3&quot;&gt;DrawingBotV3&lt;/a&gt; and photos this month - the next thing I did was to produce a card for a friends new baby, Laelia. As I discovered from Wiki, a Laelia is a type of orchid, so I downloaded this &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Laelia_rubescens#/media/File:Laelia_rubescens_Orchi_038.jpg&quot;&gt;photo&lt;/a&gt; of a Laelia Rubescens from Wiki commons and processed it with DrawingBotV3 Sobel Edges option. Some of my preprocessing decisions I regretted a bit afterwards, like dialling up the saturation to get rid of the lovely white in the flower because I was worried about having uncoloured areas in the final plot - maybe it would have worked ok like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Original photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/user:Orchi&quot;&gt;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/user:Orchi&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20220501/Laelia_rubescens_Orchi_038.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Laelia_rubescens_Orchi_038.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the result, plotted on Fabriano Disegno 4 paper, using Sharpies and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cultpens.com/i/q/UN02216/uni-pin-drawing-pen-black&quot;&gt;0.1mm Unipin fineliner&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20220501/orchid_card.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;orchid_card.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then tried the same gcode with a Unipin plus some Marabou Creabox watercolour pens from Lidl. I was expecting a nice line and wash effect - the Unipin has “Water and Fade Proof” printed on the barrel, and the website claims “Solid, pigment ink line can easily be used with watercolour as the ink will not smudge when wet”. However it didn’t stand up to a couple of hours of pen plotting (the paper did though, which is progress!). I do like the result - it reminds me of Batik:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Pen plot created using &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/drawingbotv3?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#drawingbotv3&lt;/a&gt; Sobel Edges option. The black pen was supposed to be waterproof but didn&amp;#39;t stand up to this - all good though&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeknotes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#weeknotes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/happyaccident?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#happyaccident&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/V5wgrgOzIg&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/V5wgrgOzIg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jackie Pease (@jackie_pease) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/1508213445367377921?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;March 27, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more experimient with the orchid gcode - I plotted on the reverse of some photo paper with Marabou Creabox Sketch Pens, also from Lidl. I don’t like the result as a whole but there are some interesting parts. In general the first layer comes out fainter than on normal paper e.g. the pink areas, but where there is more than one colour in a region the new ink tends to push the previous one around. Not good for reproducing what’s in the photo, but could work for something more abstract:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20220501/alcohol_on_photo_paper.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;alcohol_on_photo_paper.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a detail:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20220501/photo_paper_detail.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;photo_paper_detail.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it was on to another photo-based plotting project. I took a bike ride along to Westminster Road to take photos of this &lt;a href=&quot;https://historicengland.org.uk/listing/the-list/list-entry/1392283&quot;&gt;historic former police/fire station&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20220501/westminster_road.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;westminster_road.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20220501/westminster_road_bird.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;westminster_road_bird.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I started plotting from them (DrawingBotV3 SobelLines and Sketch Squares options).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This plot was with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cultpens.com/i/q/UN00907/uni-ball-eye-rollerball-pen-ub-157&quot;&gt;Uniball Eye pens&lt;/a&gt; (blue and pink), 0.1mm Unipin fineliner (dark grey) and 0.3mm Rotring pen with yellow Diamine ink(as the only other yellow pens I had were Sharpies). I love the way the sky has turned out, but the building shouldn’t look as grey. The Uniball Eye pens are very fine so often last for a couple of prints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20220501/fire_station_portrait.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;fire_station_portrait.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I increased the amount of red using the DrawingBotV3 preprocessor and tried again, using these &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cultpens.com/i/q/UN86996/uni-ball-on-point-one-dream-gel-pen-3-pack&quot;&gt;Uni-ball On Point One Dream Gel Pens&lt;/a&gt; - expensive, but they do claim to be fade proof and this 3 pack actually has a useful colour range:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20220501/uniball_one.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;uniball_one.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used a 0.1mm dark grey Unipin as key, but it ran out so I went over it with 0.5mm. It doesn’t look as pretty but the result is easier to read ( 0.5mm was specified in DrawingBotV3):
&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20220501/fire_station_square.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;fire_station_square.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a couple of plots I did of the Liver Bird on the corner of the building, firstly in the Uni-ball Ones plus a UniPin 0.5mm in dark grey, then in black and light grey 0.5mm Unipins:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20220501/Bird_triangles.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bird_triangles.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20220501/Bird_greyscale.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bird_greyscale.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The light grey Unipin didn’t seem to have the same quality of ink as the black one, and the tip seemed to deteriorate during the plot (also the grey pen must have been knocked during plotting …).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do have a few non-pen plotter related things to mention (it has been about 6 weeks since my last blog post after all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/robotorium/&quot;&gt;Snoof&lt;/a&gt; showed us how to make these paper flowers at DoESLiverpool &lt;a href=&quot;https://doesliverpool.com/maker-events/&quot;&gt;makerday&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Some of the flowers that I (and others) made at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Robotorium?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Robotorium&lt;/a&gt; impromptu paper flower tutorial yesterday &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DoESLiverpool?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@DoESLiverpool&lt;/a&gt; makerday - thanks Snoof!&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeknotes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#weeknotes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/LVA8ZoyJeV&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/LVA8ZoyJeV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jackie Pease (@jackie_pease) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/1513047444786974720?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 10, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started looking into making something sparkly for summer using waste plastics at &lt;a href=&quot;https://plastictactics.com/&quot;&gt;Plastic Tactics&lt;/a&gt; Plastic Playgroup:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Prototype &amp;quot;sashiko&amp;quot; in crisp packet &amp;quot;plarn&amp;quot; on ironed-together plastic bags with laser-cut holes. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/PixiesInSpace?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@PixiesInSpace&lt;/a&gt;, who did the sewing, said it made her hands hurt though, so I need to think of some improvements before Sunday afternoon&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/plastacs?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@plastacs&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/plasticplaygroup?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#plasticplaygroup&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br /&gt;Ideas welcome! &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/0ieCpkrbFE&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/0ieCpkrbFE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jackie Pease (@jackie_pease) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/1517123059924324353?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 21, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also for Plastic Playgroup, I talked a bit about making the Plastic Flowers in this radio clip (worth listening to for &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/arthrowl&quot;&gt;Arthur’s&lt;/a&gt; explanation of why he set up Plastic Tactics and what he hopes people will get from it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Here&amp;#39;s the clip, and a pic of the award we made, for those who couldn&amp;#39;t listen live to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bbcmerseyside?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@bbcmerseyside&lt;/a&gt; piece by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/chamiltonbbc?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@chamiltonbbc&lt;/a&gt; about their experience at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/PlasticPlaygroup?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#PlasticPlaygroup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/nBRo2QbRoz&quot;&gt;https://t.co/nBRo2QbRoz&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/J0VTNnvaM9&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/J0VTNnvaM9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Plastic Tactics (@plastacs) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/plastacs/status/1519282787731263489?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 27, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of the Plastic Flowers, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mynameismwd.org/&quot;&gt;Michael Dales&lt;/a&gt; took a really good photo on a recent visit to DoES Liverpool:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20220501/md_plastic_flowers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;md_plastic_flowers.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, on this Friday’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pelotonliv&quot;&gt;Peloton Liverpool&lt;/a&gt; ride, we got the chance to find out more about the work of &lt;a href=&quot;https://wheelsforall.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Wheels for All Merseyside&lt;/a&gt; and try out some of their bikes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;A pleasure joining up with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/PelotonLiv?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@PelotonLiv&lt;/a&gt; last night. Lovely to have a ride together with some of our inclusive cyclists, and to show the group what we do every day of the week across Merseyside &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/7yrPDvWb64&quot;&gt;https://t.co/7yrPDvWb64&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Wheels for All Merseyside (@WFAMerseyside) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WFAMerseyside/status/1520431809263280128?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 30, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2022/05/01/Weeknotes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2022/05/01/Weeknotes.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>weeknotes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week Notes - Solidarity in Neopixels</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A month since my last “weeknotes”, so quite a lot to write about. Firstly Mike G replaced the original power cables we’d used for the Plastic Flowers with white ones. We covered these with netting tube known as “millinery crin” which we’d first seen when makers from DoES Liverpool were involved in this project for Batala Mersey drummers with Uma and Mandy from Brouhaha International.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BatalaMersey?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@batalamersey&lt;/a&gt; drummers with backpacks by Mandy and Uma from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Brouhaha_Int?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Brouhaha_int&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/neopixel?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#neopixel&lt;/a&gt; spirals (not switched on yet) by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/zarino?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@zarino&lt;/a&gt;, me, and lots of other people &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DoESLiverpool?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@DoESLiverpool&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/MakersHour?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#MakersHour&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeknotes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#weeknotes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/ejHZwvLkpZ&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/ejHZwvLkpZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jackie Pease (@jackie_pease) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/996839411315863552?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 16, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a link for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parkinfabrics.co.uk/millinery/trimmings/crin/crin-tube.html&quot;&gt;millinery crin&lt;/a&gt;, in case it’s useful to anyone who wants to tidy up some cables, and here’s another picture of the Plastic Flowers, now with new power cable (any excuse):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Thanks to Mike G for attaching a new white lead to my &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/plasticflowers?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#plasticflowers&lt;/a&gt; (so it doesn&amp;#39;t show up against white surfaces), and mending a couple of broken stems. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeknotes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#weeknotes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/dZ7tOMowK0&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/dZ7tOMowK0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jackie Pease (@jackie_pease) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/1497647401015910402?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 26, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was pretty convinced at the time of my last weeknotes that the issues we were having with McGraw, the DoES Liverpool pen plotter, were finally resolved, but this turned out not to be the case, and quite a lot of time has been spent on this in the last few weeks (and not just by me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly Pablo 3d printed an attachment to keep the penholder more steady (McGraw used to be a laser engraving machine, so wasn’t designed to cope with the friction between pen and paper):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;More pen plotter testing today. Pablo printed an extra wheel attachment for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DoESLiverpool?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@doesliverpool&lt;/a&gt; penplotter, McGraw, to stabilise the pen holder. &lt;br /&gt;There are still some artefacts in the print though - the next thing to try is cleaning the belts and bearings with IPA&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeknotes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#weeknotes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/hedIwXW5sj&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/hedIwXW5sj&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jackie Pease (@jackie_pease) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/1498083523139362816?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 27, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then took the plotter to bits, replaced the upper belts, and cleaned the bearings and track with IPA:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Cleaning McGraw, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DoESLiverpool?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@DoESLiverpool&lt;/a&gt; pen plotter and replacing some of the toothed belts. It definitely needed it! &lt;br /&gt;Lines seem a lot smoother again now, but there&amp;#39;s still a bit of work to do.&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeknotes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#weeknotes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/nbg1BdrSWp&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/nbg1BdrSWp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jackie Pease (@jackie_pease) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/1500565760221057024?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;March 6, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After putting it back together, the limit switches didn’t work, so thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/epsaul&quot;&gt;Ed Saul&lt;/a&gt; for noticing that the Nano controller wasn’t seated properly…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;A few pictures from this week: Emre and Fatih heat pressing garment vinyl, Nathalie with tote bag, Ed and Mike debugging McGraw the pen plotter, Karen ironing sheets of soft plastic&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeknotes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#weeknotes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/HwqRvoDJ6a&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/HwqRvoDJ6a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; DoES Liverpool (@DoESLiverpool) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DoESLiverpool/status/1503134742757232645?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;March 13, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now the plotter is working fine, and we can get on with using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to LEDs then - the “disco breast plates” I helped create for &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/PelotonLiv&quot;&gt;Peloton Liverpool&lt;/a&gt; had been displaying the same pattern since they were delivered in November. Danny got in touch to say he’d like them to show the colours of the Ukrainian flag:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Joy ride tonight with students of University of Liverpool. On the last one we had 7 countries represented. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If you see us, give us a friendly beep. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Thanks &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@jackie_pease&lt;/a&gt; for reprogramming our lights. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/myGRze2sPD&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/myGRze2sPD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Danny, part of the Peloton (@PelotonLiv) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/PelotonLiv/status/1499019125011668996?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;March 2, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t stop a war with LEDs, unfortunately, but it did spark conversation about the subject at Friday night’s Joy Ride cycling group, and passers-by were interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, last week, I used a Pico with &lt;a href=&quot;https://shop.pimoroni.com/products/pico-unicorn-pack?variant=32369501306963&quot;&gt;Pimoroni Pico Unicorn Pack&lt;/a&gt; that I already had to make this &lt;a href=&quot;https://magpi.raspberrypi.com/articles/build-a-pico-pomodoro-timer&quot;&gt;Pomodoro timer&lt;/a&gt; I saw featured in MagPi magazine. A quick and simple project and a potentially useful output - the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oliverburkeman.com/time&quot;&gt;Pomodoro method&lt;/a&gt; aims to improve productivity by breaking up your work time into 25 minute tranches with 5 minute breaks. I’ve attached it to my work computer and will report on any positive changes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2022/03/14/Weeknotes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2022/03/14/Weeknotes.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>weeknotes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week Notes - Straighter Lines</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent some time this fortnight trying to install the latest version of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Aircoookie/WLED/&quot;&gt;WLED firmware&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tindie.com/products/mcqn_ltd/my-babys-got-led/&quot;&gt;My Baby’s Got LED board&lt;/a&gt; which controls my &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/1485331378178777092?s=20&amp;amp;t=kq-CDlgLHMO2QyK8yB9Mnw&quot;&gt;#plasticflowers&lt;/a&gt; (each flower contains a ring of 8 WS2812 RGB pixels, so I’ll be able to use the new grid feature to set them up as an 8 x 45 grid and light them up individually). This has proved more challenging than I’d hoped, so I’m putting that to one side for a while (they do look ok as they are).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have made more progress with pen plotting though. A conversation at DoES Liverpool’s maker night led to the realisation that most of the wobbliness of the lines was due to dirt on the the bearings. These have now been cleaned and the plotter is working a lot better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Better results from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DoESLiverpool?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@DoESLiverpool&lt;/a&gt; penplotter &amp;quot;McGraw&amp;quot; now the wheels have been cleaned (picture in orange is &amp;quot;before&amp;quot;, although it looks like my phone has &lt;br /&gt; straightened the wobbly lines).&lt;br /&gt;Still looking at a small amount of movement where the penholder is attached &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeknotes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#weeknotes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/jdn1KFSryC&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/jdn1KFSryC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jackie Pease (@jackie_pease) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/1493307445141282816?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 14, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s possibly still a bit of movement where the penholder is attached, we’re looking at adding another bearing to counteract that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also made some pen storage, using one of the parametric designes at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.festi.info/boxes.py/&quot;&gt;https://www.festi.info/boxes.py/&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve sized this one for thicker marker pens, and will probably make one with smaller holes for thinner pens, and one for ink:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Stackable pen storage for pen plotter supplies, laser cut from a parametric design from &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/oSn10YAFnB&quot;&gt;https://t.co/oSn10YAFnB&lt;/a&gt; - a really useful site, often used &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DoESLiverpool?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@DoESLiverpool&lt;/a&gt; to make boxes for electronics etc.&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeknotes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#weeknotes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/R7CyK0eZIw&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/R7CyK0eZIw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jackie Pease (@jackie_pease) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/1492926849973985283?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 13, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’ve got the right paper and pen combination, a more accurate pen plotter, and storage for some of the pens, it’s probably time to start thinking about some new things to plot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also found out last week that some gears I’d printed in August for the tattoo parlour in the same building as DoES Liverpool were now in use. They’re in old bubble gum machines being used to dispense tattoo designs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I&amp;#39;ve finally seen the machines in situ, in working order dispensing tattoo designs! &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeknotes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#weeknotes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/EBQuJOnnge&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/EBQuJOnnge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jackie Pease (@jackie_pease) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/1490360208299855878?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 6, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good to be able to help bring these old machines back to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And last but not least, I’ve been doing my bit towards publicising DoES Liverpool’s Boost membership scheme, to help widen access to this amazing coworking and maker space. If you know anyone in the Liverpool area who might benefit, then please tell them about it…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;We&amp;#39;re accepting applications until the end of February for our second cohort of free Boost members. Find out more here:&lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/vczCHrcWYl&quot;&gt;https://t.co/vczCHrcWYl&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/GOMNEfy4tl&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/GOMNEfy4tl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; DoES Liverpool (@DoESLiverpool) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DoESLiverpool/status/1492780165059039241?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;February 13, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I’m just going to call these weeknotes now, however often I do them (it’s been two weeks this time, which does make it easier to find something to write about).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2022/02/14/Weeknotes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2022/02/14/Weeknotes.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>weeknotes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fortnight Notes - More on Plastic Flowers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At the time of my last blog post, the Plastic Flowers had been carefully positioned in the base grid, a difficult job as they’re pretty fragile, so thanks again Sanna!:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/fortnightnotes_20220130/flower_stand_with_wires.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;flower_stand_with_wires.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, that still left a lot of wiring to be done. Mike G again volunteered to help with this, a task which apparently made him feel nostalgic for his time wiring up telephone exchanges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/fortnightnotes_20220130/mike_working_on_flower_electronics.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;mike_working_on_flower_electronics.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also made a box to hold the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tindie.com/products/mcqn_ltd/my-babys-got-led/&quot;&gt;My Baby’s Got LED board&lt;/a&gt; and the PC power supply it runs off, based on one Arthur made for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mcqn.com/posts/weeks-821-822-questioning-a-mastodon-+-boxing-a-liver-bird/&quot;&gt;Electric Liver Bird&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/fortnightnotes_20220130/power_supply_box.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;power_supply_box.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The My Baby’s Got LED board lets you easily set up addressable LEDs to be controlled by &lt;a href=&quot;https://kno.wled.ge/&quot;&gt;WLED software&lt;/a&gt;. You can run WLED from a phone app over Wifi, so once it was set up, it didn’t take much to try out different effects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Afternoon spent wiring up the LEDs on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/plasticflowers?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#plasticflowers&lt;/a&gt; with Mike G at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/plastacs?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@plastacs&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/plasticplaygroup?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#plasticplaygroup&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DoESLiverpool?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@doesliverpool&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;They all seem to work - just the back to tidy up now and make a box for the power supply&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/wled?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#wled&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ws2812?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#ws2812&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/mybabysgotledboard?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#mybabysgotledboard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeknotes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#weeknotes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/xLWVUJ5Wli&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/xLWVUJ5Wli&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jackie Pease (@jackie_pease) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/1485331378178777092?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;January 23, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/fortnightnotes_20220130/flowers_in_various_colours.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;flowers_in_various_colours.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/fortnightnotes_20220130/flowers_in_white.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;flowers_in_white.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Left to do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update the My Baby’s Got LED board to the latest version of the WLED software (I’ve had it for a while now, and a lots happened with WLED in the meantime). This will let me set up the flowers as a 8 x 45 grid (there are 8 LEDs in each flower), so that each flower can be a different colour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look into the sound reactive option in WLED as well, so that the flowers can react to music&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mike has suggested redoing the cables from the vase to the power supply in white so that they don’t show up against white table cloths at events (it seems like they might be the sort of think people would want to use at events, and you could even get them to match your bridesmaids’ dresses if you wanted…).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other news, the paper I ordered at the end of December eventually arrived (after a complaint), and Ed at DoES Liverpool lent me some lovely old technical pens, so I did some more experimenting with pen and paper options for the pen plotter. One of the pens was 2mm, so puts down a lot of ink, meaning that the paper stays quite damp. This seemed like a good test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.greatart.co.uk/fabriano-bristol-paper.html&quot;&gt;Bristol board&lt;/a&gt; didn’t really stand up to the task, with quite large areas of damaged paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/fortnightnotes_20220130/bristol_board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bristol_board.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.greatart.co.uk/fabriano-disegno-4-drawing-paper.html&quot;&gt;Fabriano Disegno 4 drawing paper&lt;/a&gt;, marketed as “extremely resistant to erasing, scratches and scrapes”, unsurprisingly did a lot better, with only small areas where the surface was slightly damaged:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/fortnightnotes_20220130/disegno_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;disegno_4.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d definitely recommend the Disegno 4, and I won’t give up on the Bristol board yet either; it seems to be what everyone in the pen plotter community uses so I’m sure I’ll be able to find out what works with it. The overlapping lines from the thicker pen, and even the ink-saturated and scratched surface are things I’ll look at using again too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was doing these experiments, Pablo, a new member of the DoES Liverpool community, came over to take a look at the pen plotter, and has some ideas on reducing the amount of wobble in the lines. So that’s what we’re going to be looking at next Sunday afternoon - and hopefully I’ll have some excellent new pen plots for my next WeekNotes.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jan 2022 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2022/01/30/Weeknotes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2022/01/30/Weeknotes.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>weeknotes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Month Notes - Progress with the Plastic Flowers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I thought I’d slightly sabotaged my pen plotting project recently by getting qualms about the number of disposable pens I was getting through, but trying out various reusable alternatives instead is proving just as interesting. I’ve done more with the Rotring technical pens and Lamy fountain pens which I had already, and I’ve bought &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cultpens.com/i/q/PL01289/pilot-parallel-pen&quot;&gt;Pilot Parallel Pens&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem I’ve had is that finer pens (and water based ones) tend to dig up the paper. It looks as if you just can’t use more than 2 - 3 layers, but I’ve also ordered some tougher paper. This might be followed by some new ink, as only some are properly permanent - Rev Dan Catt mentions Noodler’s Bulletproof in this Instagram &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CYj10z4tQ1a/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s some of the output. The first 2 are based on this Andy Wallace &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Andy_Makes/status/1470549299020943360?s=20&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; and this Keith Peters &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bit-101.com/blog/2017/10/flow-fields-part-i/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; and plotted in technical pen on card and calligraphy paper respectively. The card has been badly dug up. The calligraphy paper did better, although the blue ink stopped flowing half way through the second part for some reason, and the lines are a bit wobbly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/monthnotes_20220117/circles_plot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;circles_plot.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/monthnotes_20220117/bit101-flowfields.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bit101-flowfields.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Pilot pen arrived I didn’t have anything ready to plot, except a dxf grid for the plastic flowers. I wrote a bash script to convert it to gcode using vPype, Juicy GCode and the vpype-dxf extension:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for &lt;/span&gt;x &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$@&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;do
   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt; | &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cut&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-f&lt;/span&gt; 1 &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&apos;.&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$f&lt;/span&gt;
   vpype dread &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$f&lt;/span&gt;.dxf scaleto &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-f&lt;/span&gt; 250mm 250mm linesort write &lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
           &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--page-size&lt;/span&gt; a3 &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--landscape&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--center&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-out&lt;/span&gt;.svg
   vpype &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;read&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-out&lt;/span&gt;.svg ldelete 2 write &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-out2&lt;/span&gt;.svg
   juicy-gcode &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-out2&lt;/span&gt;.svg &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-f&lt;/span&gt; flavor.txt &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-o&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$f&lt;/span&gt;.gcode
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Juicy GCode needs a config file called flavor.txt, in the same folder. Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-bash highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;gcode
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
   begin &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;G17;G21;G28;G90;G1 F400;M3 S05;G4 P0.3&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
   end &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;M3 S05;G4 P0.3;G1 X.000 Y.000&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
   toolon &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;M3 S120;G4 P0.3&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
   tooloff &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;M3 S05;G4 P0.3&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pen worked really well on cartridge paper with a lovely smooth red (there’s some Sharpie on there too - I need to use them up!):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/monthnotes_20220117/pilot_pen_on_cartridge_paper.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pilot_pen_on_cartridge_paper.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On calligraphy paper it was less smooth, but still a nice effect:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/monthnotes_20220117/pilot_pen_on_calligraphy_paper.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pilot_pen_on_calligraphy_paper.jpg&quot; /&gt;
~                                                                                                                      &lt;br /&gt;
I’ve had to take a break from pen plotting to make progress on the Plastic Flowers, which were cluttering up Room 29 at DoES Liverpool. In order to fill the light fitting / vase, I need 40ish flowers so laser cutting stems and hand cutting and heat pressing milk carton petals has taken a while. This week I’ve been lucky to have help from Sanna King and Mike Gorman, with assembly and soldering, so progress has been a lot quicker than it would have been otherwise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Lots of thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sanna_king?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@sanna_king&lt;/a&gt; (shown)and Mike G for helping me with my light up up plastic flowers this week. &lt;br /&gt;&amp;#39;Only&amp;#39; the wiring to go now. Hopefully it will be finished soon!&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/weeknotes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#weeknotes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/bU70S1Pr8M&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/bU70S1Pr8M&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jackie Pease (@jackie_pease) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/1482844377131241479?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;January 16, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Peloton disk lights I’ve been working on recently have been deployed successfully on 3 occasions now, including this Peloton Liverpool trip to Kirby:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Lovely &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/PelotonLiv?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@PelotonLiv&lt;/a&gt; Friday night &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/joyride?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#joyride&lt;/a&gt; to Kirby to visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cultureKnowsley?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@cultureKnowsley&lt;/a&gt; light installation &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/aqualux?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#aqualux&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/DRcTuXQvaG&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/DRcTuXQvaG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jackie Pease (@jackie_pease) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackie_pease/status/1482262962219978754?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;January 15, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately there’s been a slight issue, obvious in this photo of Arthur at that ride. The light disks were attached to wooden spacers and those were attached to the backs with carpet tape… This issue didn’t show up in the earlier sets until they’d been in use for a couple of weeks. So I think I’m going to be gradually going through all the sets if and when they fail, using a scalpel to prise apart the VHB tape round the edges, and replacing the wood and carpet tape with acrylic and VHB …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/monthnotes_20220117/arthur.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;arthur.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2022/01/17/Weeknotes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2022/01/17/Weeknotes.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>weeknotes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Week Notes - Plotting with Refillable Pens</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve been spending a lot of my free time working on these &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/amcewen/status/1467598114559299588?s=20&quot;&gt;lights&lt;/a&gt;, along with other members of the  &lt;a href=&quot;https://doesliverpool.com/&quot;&gt;DoES Liverpool&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://peloton.coop/&quot;&gt;Peloton Liverpool&lt;/a&gt; communities; now they’re in action I’ve had a chance to get back to a bit of pen plotting (I am going to do a blog post on the lights once I get a few more photos together though, and there’s definitely more work to do in the future to take full advantage of the MCQN Ltd “&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mcqn/my-bikes-got-led&quot;&gt;My Bikes Got LED&lt;/a&gt;” boards that control them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have any new code to plot at the moment, so thought I’d start off with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SonarSonic/DrawingBotV3&quot;&gt;DrawingBotV3&lt;/a&gt; again - I had some photos of this climbing plant that I’d taken back at the beginning of October but hadn’t got far with plotting at the time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20211213/creeper_photo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;creeper_photo.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annoyingly, I had to spend the first day resolving hardware issues: trying to work out why I was getting errors from one of the limit switches (this somehow spontaneously resolved), and replacing the servo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my first plot of the week, using Sharpies and an InkJoy fineliner:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20211213/sharpies.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;sharpies.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a bit disappointed with the outcome - there’s a blue diagonal line across the picture, the thickness of the Sharpie lines against the white background make it difficult to see the image, and the registration is really bad. It felt like I’d forgotten everything I’d learned so far. I’ve now fixed the registration problem - I’d set up the bar that keeps the cables out of the way so one end was interfering with the pen holder moving back to the origin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I wanted to experiment with refillable ink pens, as I’ve been shocked by the number of disposable pens I’ve been getting through. I’d used Rotring technical pens before with Rotring ink but seen on Instagram that some people were using fountain pen ink, which is cheaper and comes in more colours. I set the feedrate to 400 to try to avoid breaking the Rotring nibs (something that’s happened before) and this was the output after around 7 hours, using Diamine fountain pen ink in “Ancient Copper” on smooth white card:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20211213/damage_to_paper.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;damage_to_paper.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite a pretty outcome, but this should have been the first colour out of 4, and the surface of the card was already badly shredded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I tried some Yupo - which is polyester sheet, not paper, and is strong with a very smooth surface. This is the result with Diamine fountain pen ink in “Claret”. Hardly any ink is absorbed by the Yupo, leading to a very pale colour. At least there’s less chance of the ink running out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20211213/fountain_pen_ink_yupo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;fountain_pen_ink_yupo.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a Rotring pen already filled with Rotring-alike ink so I tried that. It came out a lot darker than fountain pen ink, but still not as dark as it would have on paper. Because the picture didn’t look finished, I plotted the Magenta layer with the Diamine Claret ink:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20211213/drawing_ink_yupo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;drawing_ink_yupo.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again quite a pretty effect, and this time I managed two layers (the second one took  11 hours), but the Yupo surface was still quite rough and damaged in places:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20211213/completed_yupo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;completed_yupo.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20211213/damage_to_yupo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;damage_to_yupo.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what I’ve learned is that I’m not going to get the sort of super-saturated effects from Rotring pens that I can get from the faster-drying solvent-based ink in Sharpies, although they might be ok for more geometric patterns where there isn’t much overlap betweeen lines. I think my next plot will be something like that, and I’ve also got a couple of fountain pens that I’m going to experiment with. I’ve been given some disposable pipettes so I can also try cutting off the end of a pen cartridge, putting some pauses in the gcode, and adding different coloured inks as the plot progresses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, I went to &lt;a href=&quot;https://plastictactics.com/&quot;&gt;Plastic Tactics&lt;/a&gt; Plastic Playgroup, and made some more milk carton petals for a bigger version of these &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CTK_ezwsrnH/&quot;&gt;light up plastic flowers&lt;/a&gt;, another project I’d like to make some progress on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/weeknotes_20211213/petals.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;petals.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next to laser cut some more stems from scrap ply, and then add lights…
~&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2021 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2021/12/12/WeekNotes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/weeknotes/2021/12/12/WeekNotes.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>weeknotes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DrawingBotV3 - Plotting without Coding</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the pen plotter at DoES Liverpool. It’s an A3 laser engraver base with a penholder and servo attached. I’ve been working on it`for a while now, and have mainly been learning about p5js and using it to produce &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/JackiePease/p5js-sketches&quot;&gt;geometry-based patterns&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/plotting_without_code/plotter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;plotter.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve been experimenting with ways people could use the plotter if they didn’t want to write code. One interesting piece of software I found is DrawingBotV3, which gives you a wide range of ways to produce interesting effects from bitmap files (inc. jpeg and png).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can download the software here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SonarSonic/DrawingBotV3&quot;&gt;DrawingBotV3&lt;/a&gt; - it’s available for Linux, Windows and Mac, and the installation instructions are in the ReadMe section at the bottom of the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you just need to find a photo you want to make a picture from, or create your own bitmap file. Here I’ve used Inkscape with a quote (thanks to Ross Dalziel for the quote suggestion):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/plotting_without_code/ifyourenotangry.png&quot; alt=&quot;ifyourenotangry.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve used a bold font as detail is easily lost in this process, and added a background gradient so there’s something for the algorithm to pick up and so that it isn’t too uniform. I haven’t worried about the actual colours, as these will depend on the pens used when plotting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open DrawingBotV3, and from the File tab, choose “Export Settings”. For the plotter we have at DoES Liverpool you need to set the following so that the GCode (instructions sent to the machine) will lift and lower the pen and write in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/plotting_without_code/exportsettings_speedpenuppendown.png&quot; alt=&quot;exportsettings_speedpenuppendown.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I changed the feedrate to F2000 (the default is F8000, which is likely to damage some pens, but it’s definitely worth experimenting here)
The pen up and pen down setting will depend on the plotter you’re using. Currently I’m using M3 S40 for pen up and M3 S60 for pen down, but again this is subject to experimentation…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/plotting_without_code/exportsettings_direction.png&quot; alt=&quot;exportsettings_direction.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The x-direction has been changed to Negative to stop the plotter sending a mirror image - this will depend on the plotter, and whatever has been set up in firmware&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then import your picture and set the paper size and orientation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/plotting_without_code/ifyourenotangryimport.png&quot; alt=&quot;ifyourenotangryimport.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a whole load of options you can play with. Under “Path Finding Controls” select “Path Finding Module”. In this case I picked “Sketch Lines PFM”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also choose the pen settings – they’re not going to mean much unless you’ve got the pens that the program was written for, but might be good to choose a set where it’s easy to work out which pens you’re substituting (if you choose “Special” it gives you an option of CMYK separation, which I’m intending to explore next – could mean buying some more pens…).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve chosen the options you want, click “Start Plotting”, you should see a representation of the plot on your screen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/plotting_without_code/ifyourenotangryplotted.png&quot; alt=&quot;ifyourenotangryplotted.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re happy with it, choose File → Export Per/Pen → Export GCode File&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(if you do it this way, you’ll get one file per colour. I like this as it means you don’t need to plot them all at once).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also options for saving to Inkscape, which is useful if you’ve got an Axidraw (Inkscape has its own extension for exporting to GCode).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://winder.github.io/ugs_website/download/&quot;&gt;Universal GCode Sender&lt;/a&gt; to send the GCode files to the plotter (Note: only the “Classic” version works on Linux). There are many other options though, especially if you’ve got a Windows machine…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Load the files in one at a time – DrawingBotV3 default is to start with the darkest – choosing appropriate pen colours and trying to start at the same point each time (I haven’t found the ideal way to do this as yet – some pen plotters have carousels or magnetic attachments that make it easy to load and unload pens).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This photo shows the output of just the first 2 GCode files (which are both black ink):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/plotting_without_code/ifyourenotangry_blackphoto.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ifyourenotangry_blackphoto.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and this is the final result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/plotting_without_code/ifyourenotangry_colourphoto.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ifyourenotangry_colourphoto.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I prefer the black and white version though!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried a few other options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is “Voronoi Triangulation”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/plotting_without_code/voronoi_triangulation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;voronoi_triangulation.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does involve a lot of lifting and lowering of the pen, which is a bit noisy if you’re sharing a room, and is also likely to wear out the servo motor that does the lifting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used “Sketch Squares PFM” for this house picture from a photo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/plotting_without_code/egerton_st_beige.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;egerton_st_beige.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and in blue….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/plotting_without_code/egerton_st_blue.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;egerton_st_blue.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The detail is really interesting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/plotting_without_code/close_up_squares.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;close_up_squares.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think DrawingBotV3 is a good starting point for pen plotting - thanks to the developers. There’s lots to experiment with in terms of input files, options within the program, and pen and paper choices, then you can go on to think about coding if that’s what you want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 May 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blogpost/2021/05/02/DrawingBotV3.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blogpost/2021/05/02/DrawingBotV3.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blogpost</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Embroidery x Glue - A Weekend of Experimenting</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A bit of experimenting, mainly last weekend, with machine embroidery and glue film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glue film was inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jarkman&quot;&gt;Richard Sewell&lt;/a&gt; who came along to the latest online &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DoESLiverpool/somebody-should/wiki/Wearable-Technology-Group&quot;&gt;DoES Liverpool Wearable Tech meetup&lt;/a&gt;, and as well as showing us his amazing &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AirGiantsHQ&quot;&gt;inflatable robots&lt;/a&gt;, also showed us some fabric folding techniques, using a stiffer fabric ironed on with &lt;a href=&quot;http://mcb-supplies.co.uk/HotMeltWoodVeneerAdhesive.html&quot;&gt;glue film&lt;/a&gt; to provide structure. I’m quite interested in folded structures e.g. this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CI1Jl_HH6uM/?igshid=nx9a0mnhp1ky&quot;&gt;tree&lt;/a&gt;, so ordered some of the glue film to try out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we’ve got a new embroidery machine, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DoESLiverpool/somebody-should/wiki/Embroidery-Machine-Fred&quot;&gt;Fred&lt;/a&gt; at DoESLiverpool, and it seemed worth looking at whether that had any potential as a way to stiffen fabric for folding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used my current favourite tool, &lt;a href=&quot;https://p5js.org/&quot;&gt;p5js&lt;/a&gt; to create an svg file (similar to the one I’d used for the tree). Admittedly this took me a lot longer than it would have taken with a CAD package, but it meant that I could easily change the number of rows and columns. I imported the file into &lt;a href=&quot;https://inkscape.org/&quot;&gt;Inkscape&lt;/a&gt; and used the &lt;a href=&quot;https://inkstitch.org/&quot;&gt;Ink/Stitch&lt;/a&gt; extension to create the .pes file used by the embroidery machine. I also exported it as as a dxf for use in the laser cutter - I love that you can the same base file with so many different CNC machines!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my first attempt, I started with 2 layers of scrap non-woven polypropylene and a layer of stabiliser. I was impressed by the way the embroidery looked, but I found it too difficult to keep the folds in position, and having lots of rows made it extra complicated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/1st_attempt_emb_column.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1st_attempt_emb_column.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/1st_attempt_back.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1st_attempt_back.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/1st_attempt_fold.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1st_attempt_fold.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gave up and tried again with a softer fabric, fewer rows and more columns. This also looked great just flat. The interesting black and white effect isn’t intentional - the bobbin hadn’t been threaded properly, so the tension was wrong and the bobbin thread showed on the front (something to try to recreate by blending colours though!):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/2nd_attempt_tension.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2nd_attempt_tension.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/2nd_attempt_front.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2nd_attempt_front.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/2nd_attempt_back.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2nd_attempt_back.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I removed the stabliser between the triangles, hoping this would give more flexibility. It was very difficult to get get the triangles to stay in position once folded, but after sticking the edges together to make a tube shape, it did eventually work (someone said this looked like a caterpillar, so that might be something to work on - I’d like to try adding servos…):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/2nd_attempt_folded.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2nd_attempt_folded.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the 3rd attempt I decided to use 2 layers of embroidery (actually 2 layers of fill stitch + 2 backing layers), made the triangles a bit bigger for easier folding and reduced the space between triangles. Disadvantages, not enough triangles round to make a column shape (this was the most that would fit in the hoop - there is a way to piece bigger embroideries together, so I’ll be looking into that), plus it uses lots of thread and is hard work for the machine. It did fold really easily and is quite a nice object to hold:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/3rd_attempt_front.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;3rd_attempt_front.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/3rd_attempt_folded.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;3rd_attempt_folded.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more go, with smaller triangles and only 1 layer of embroidery - this took a lot of manual folding before the folds fell into place, but once it did, the structure seemed pretty stable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/4th_attempt_front.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;4th_attempt_front.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/4th_attempt_folded.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;4th_attempt_folded.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whie waiting for the embroidery machine (it does take a while), I tried out the glue sheets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cut out a piece of glue sheet, then ironed it onto the back of some thick satin curtain fabric brought in by Karen, who I’m working with on another project. As Karen was laser cutting some chain maille, we decided to use that as a test:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/satin_glue.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;satin_glue.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/satin_laser_cutting.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;satin_laser_cutting.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After laser cutting, you need to remove the backing sheet, and then iron on to a substrate. We used baking paper to stop the glue sticking to the iron - the baking paper stuck to the fabric though, so not the best:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/satin_separating.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;satin_separating.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results were good, both with the left over teardrop shapes, and with the chain maille:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/satin_teardrops.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;satin_teardrops.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/satin_on_velvet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;satin_on_velvet.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then tried the folding pattern on 3mm ply. After laser cutting the ply we replaced the triangles with the glue side up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/ply_laser_cutting.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ply_laser_cutting.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/ply_glue.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ply_glue.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/ply_ironing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ply_ironing.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a fine soft fabric meant that the glue came through to the back. It also tended to spread a bit round the edges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/ply_back_fabric.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ply_back_fabric.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ply stuck well, but the output wasn’t really suitable for folding&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/ply_lifting.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ply_lifting.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/ply_on_fabric.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ply_on_fabric.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve got a lot of polypropylene at DoES Liverpool, so it seemed worth trying that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/pp_laser_cutting.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pp_laser_cutting.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It did fold quite well, but as with embroidery, it would have been better with narrower channels in between the shapes. The polypropylene stuck well to begin with, but after a few days of being flexed it began to come away from the fabric. It might be better to use something more flexible if it’s designed to be moved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/pp_folded.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pp_folded.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also ironed the waste polypropylene on to some gauze; the glue spread badly because the fabric couldn’t absorb it, and the baking paper stuck. I washed this in an attempt to remove the soot from the laser cutter (it didn’t) and the glue seemed unaffected:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/pp_gauze.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pp_gauze.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, we ironed some foil sheets onto the waste ply - this would have probably worked better if we’d waited for the glue to set, but still a pretty nice distressed effect after a couple of sheets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jackiepease.github.io/assets/embroidery_x_glue/ply_foil.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ply_foil.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not quite sure where this is going, but maybe my next step will be to try some more flexible materials with the glue method and articulating some of the folding structures.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blogpost/2021/03/21/embroidery-x-glue.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blogpost/2021/03/21/embroidery-x-glue.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>blogpost</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
